Learning-SICP学习小组
倾情制作
翻译&&时间轴：邓雄飞（Dysprosium）
压制&&特效：邓雄飞（Dysprosium）
校对：邓雄飞（Dysprosium）
特别感谢：裘宗燕教授
符号化求导系统，引用
Symbolic Differentiation: Quotation
教授：嗯 Harold教授讲解了如何构造健壮的系统
PROFESSOR: Well, Hal just told us how you build robust systems.
关键点就是
The key idea was--
我想你们大多还没吃透其中的要点
I'm sure that many of you don't really assimilate that yet--
要点就是 为了让系统具有健壮性
but the key idea is that in order to make a system that's robust,
应该让它对小变化不敏感
it has to be insensitive to small changes,
也就是说
that is,
问题中的小改变只会导致解决方案的小改动
a small change in the problem should lead to only a small change in the solution.
系统应该是连续的
There ought to be a continuity.
在问题空间中 解的空间是连续的
The space of solutions ought to be continuous in this space of problems.
Harold教授给你们解释过
The way he was explaining how to do that
与其在问题分解出的子问题上 求解具体问题
was instead of solving a particular problem at every level of decomposition of the problem at the subproblems,
你不如解决一类问题
where you solve the class of problems,
也就是你想要解决的具体问题的“邻居”
which are a neighborhood of the particular problem that you're trying to solve.
解决之道便是在该层次上构造一门语言
The way you do that is by producing a language at that level of detail
使得我们可以用这门语言来表述这类问题
in which the solutions to that class of problems is representable in that language.
因此 当着手解决的问题再发生变动时
Therefore when you change makes more changes to the problem you're trying to solve,
通常 你只需要在已构造好的解决方案上做出微小改动
you generally have to make only small local changes to the solution you've constructed,
因为在你所考虑的层次上
because at the level of detail you're working,
有一门语言可以表达
there's a language where you can express
类似问题的各种解法
the various solutions to alternate problems of the same type.
呃... 这是一个重要思想的萌芽
Well that's the beginning of a very important idea,
该思想的重要性也使得计算机科学比
the most important perhaps idea that makes computer science more powerful
其它大多数工程学科还要强大
than most of the other kinds of engineering disciplines we know about.
目前为止 我们学习的是
What we've seen so far
类似于 如何使用语言内置元素
is sort of how to use embedding of languages.
当然 内置元素的力量一部分来源于
And, of course, the power of embedding languages partly comes from
像这个一样的过程 我昨天给你们展示过了
procedures like this one that I showed you yesterday.
这里 是一份求导程序 昨天给你们描述过了
What you see here is the derivative program that we described yesterday.
这个过程以一个过程为参数
It's a procedure that takes a procedure as an argument
并返回一个过程
and returns a procedure as a value.
用这样的东西棒极了
And using such things is very nice.
你可以像创建PUSH组合子那样构造
You can make things like push combinators
可以像上节课看到的那些奇妙东西那样
and all that sort of wonderful thing that you saw last time.
现在 我要来打个太极
However, now I'm going to really muddy the waters.
这个程序混淆了过程和数据
See this confuses the issue of what's the procedure and what is data,
虽然程度不算太重
but not very badly.
而我们将要严重地混淆两者
What we really want to do is confuse it very badly.
最好的做法就是
And the best way to do that
参与到过程自身所描述的代数表达式的操作中
is to get involved with the manipulation of the algebraic expressions that the procedures themselves are expressed in.
所以 这里我不会讨论这张幻灯片上的东西
So at this point, I want to talk about instead of things like on this slide,
一个通过操作过程的求导程序
the derivative procedure being a thing that manipulates a procedure--
这只是一个数值化方法而已
this is a numerical method you see here.
你们所看到的是 通过数值方法来近似的求导程序
And what you're seeing is a representation of the numerical approximationto the derivative.
也就是这里的东西了
That's what's here.
事实上 我想讨论的是这些东西
In fact what I'd like to talk about is instead things that look like this.
这是一份从微积分书中摘录的法则
And what we have here are rules from a calculus book.
这对表达式求导的法则
These are rules for finding the derivatives of the expressions
只不过是用代数语言书写的
that one might write in some algebraic language.
法则说 常数的导数是0
It says things like a derivative of a constant is 0.
而代表你所讨论的那个数的变量导数为1
The derivative of the valuable with respect to which you are taking the derivative is 1.
常数乘以函数的导数
The derivative of a constant times the function
其值是常数的值乘以函数导数的值
is the constant times the derivative of the function,
就是这个意思
and things like that.
这些都是精确的表达式 而非数值近似
These are exact expressions. These are not numerical approximations.
我们还能编写程序吗？
Can we make programs?
事实上 编写处理这些表达式的程序非常容易
And, in fact, it's very easy to make programs that manipulate these expressions.
让我们仔细地看看这些法则
Well let's see. Let's look at these rules in some detail.
你们曾经在初等微积分课上学过这些法则了
You all have seen these rules in your elementary calculus class at one time or another.
你们知道 微积分中对多元表达式求导很容易
And you know from calculus that it's easy to produce derivatives of arbitrary expressions.
在微积分课上 你们也知道计算积分不容易
You also know from your elementary calculus that it's hard to produce integrals.
虽然积分和求导相对
Yet integrals and derivatives are opposites of each other.
它俩互为逆运算
They're inverse operations.
但它们有同样的法则
And they have the same rules.
但这些法则中又有什么特殊的东西
What is special about these rules that makes it possible for one
使得求导容易 求积分就困难呢？
to produce derivatives easily and integrals why it's so hard?
我们浅显地想一想
Let's think about that very simply.
仔细考察法则
Look at these rules.
对于每条法则来说 你求导数时的方向
Every one of these rules, when used in the direction for taking derivatives,
这个箭头的方向
which is in the direction of this arrow,
法则的左边与你的表达式相匹配
the left side is matched against your expression,
法则的右边就是表达式的导数
and the right side is the thing which is the derivative of that expression.
箭头是这个方向的
The arrow is going that way.
每条法则中
In each of these rules,
法则右边的表达式
the expressions on the right-hand side of the rule
都是求导过程中的子表达式
that are contained within derivatives are subexpressions,
都是左边式子的合法子表达式
are proper subexpressions, of the expression on the left-hand side.
这里 我们发现 和的导数
So here we see the derivative of the sum,
也就是左边式子的导数
witch is the expression on the left-hand side
就是两部分导数之和
is the sum of the derivatives of the pieces.
法则从左至右的方向是“归约规则”
So the rule of moving to the right are reduction rules.
问题变简单了
The problem becomes easier.
我把一个复杂的问题 转化成了许多小点儿的问题
I make, I turn a big complicated problem it's lots of smaller problems
然后把结果组合起来 这里用递归可以完美地解决
and then combine the results, a perfect place for recursion to work.
但如果我从另外的方向来思考
If I'm going in the other direction like this,
如果我想求积分的话 你会发现有很多问题
if I'm trying to produce integrals, well there are several problems you see here.
就比如 如果我想求一个和的积分
First of all, if I try to integrate an expression like a sum,
就会匹配多条法则
more than one rule matches.
这条匹配
Here's one that matches.
这条也匹配
我不知道该用哪个——它们之间可能不一样
I don't know which one to take. And they may be different.
我得考察两者的不同之处
I may get to explore different things.
所以 在这个方向上 表达式变复杂了
Also, the expressions become larger in that direction.
当表达式变复杂时
And when the expressions become larger,
就没法保证我所选的路径一定能终止了
then there's no guarantee that any particular path I choose will terminate,
因为唯一的可能是偶然的约分
because we will only terminate by accidental cancellation.
这也就是为什么 积分是一种复杂的搜索 而难以完成
So that's why integrals are complicated searches and hard to do.
现在我不想处理这么复杂的东西
Right now I don't want to do anything as hard as that.
我们先来讨论求导数
Let's work on derivatives for a while.
好吧 我就假设你们都大致了解这些法则了
Well, these rules are ones you know for the most part hopefully.
让我们来看看能不能用程序表达这些法则
So let's see if we can write a program which is these rules.
这应该很容易
And that should be very easy.
信手拈来
Just write the program.
因为 我给你们展示的是“归约规则”
See, because while I showed you is that it's a reduction rule,
这样用递归来编写会比较合适
it's something appropriate for a recursion.
当然 对每条法则来说就是一种情况
And, of course, what we have for each of these rules is we have a case
我们做“分情况分析”
in some case analysis.
我就这么写了
So I'm just going to write this program down.
当然 我得先让大家达成共识 对吧？
Now, of course, I'm going to be saying something you have to believe. Right?
你们应该意识到到我可以表示这些代数式
What you have to believe is I can represent these algebraic expressions,
我可以从中抽取式子 也可以将它们组合起来
that I can grab their parts, that I can put them together.
我们发明了表结构来解决这个问题
We've invented list structures so that you can do that.
但现在我们不必关心
But you don't want to worry about that now.
现在 我要编写一个程序来封装这些法则
Right now I'm going to write the program that encapsulates these rules
但它不依赖于代数表达式的表示法
independent of the representation of the algebraic expressions.
(DERIV EXP VAR)表示表达式EXP关于变量VAR的导数
You have a derivative of an expression with respect to a variable.
这和函数的导数是不一样的
This is a different thing than the derivative of the function.
那个是我们上节课看到的数值近似
That's what we saw last time, that numerical approximation.
并不能看到函数内部
It's something you can't open up a function.
它只是一个数值
It's just the answers.
表达式的导数也是一个表达式
The derivative of an expression is the way it's written.
因此 这只是一个语法问题
And therefore it's a syntactic phenomenon.
我们今天要做的大多数工作 就是讨论语法
And so a lot of what we're going to be doing today is worrying about syntax,
表达式的语法或类似
syntax of expressions and things like that.
首先要做“分情况分析”
Well, there's a case analysis.
任何时候我们处理复杂事物 需要递归求解时
Anytime we do anything complicated thereby a recursion,
我们很可能需要“按情况分析”
we presumably need a case analysis.
通常都是这样开始的
It's the essential way to begin.
复杂的问题都是用“按情况分析”
And that's usually a conditional of some large kind.
那么 有哪些可能（的情况）呢？
Well, what are their possibilities?
第一条法则说 如果你遇到一个常数
the first rule that you saw is this something a constant?
这里 我就是在判断
And what I'm asking is,
表达式EXP是否为给定变量VAR的常数（常量表达式）
is the expression a constant with respect to the variable given?
是的话 结果就是0
If so, the result is 0,
因为导数表征的是某物的变化率
because the derivative represents the rate of change of something.
然而
If, however,
如果我求导的表达式 与我关心的变量有关
the expression that I'm taking the derivative of is the variable I'm varying,
如果判定表达式和变量相同
then this is the same variable, the expression var,
那么关于变量VAR的表达式EXP的变化率就是1
then the rate of change of the expression with respect to the variable is 1.
它俩相同 结果是1
It's the same 1.
当然 还可能有其它的可能性
Well now there are a couple of other possibilities.
比如说 它可能是一个和式
It could, for example, be a sum.
呃 我现在还完全知道该如何表示和式
Well, I don't know how I'm going to express sums yet.
事实上我可以 只是我还没有告诉你们
Actually I do. But I haven't told you yet.
如果表达式是和式
But is it a sum?
我就假想有一种方式可以判别（和式）
I'm imagining that there's some way of telling.
这里 我要做一个表达式的类型分派
I'm doing a dispatch on the type of the expression here,
这是在构建语言时绝对必要的
absolutely essential in building languages.
因为语言由不同的表达式构成
Cause languages are made out of different expressions.
我们马上就将看到
And soon we're going to see that
如何用更强大的方法 用语言去构建语言
in our more powerful methods of building languages on languages.
表达式是和式吗？
Is an expression a sum?
如果是的话 很好 我们已经知道和式的求导法则了
If it's a sum, well, we know the rule for derivative of the sum
即是各部分导数之和
is the sum of the derivatives of the parts.
其中一个叫做加数 另一个叫做被加数
One of them is called the addend and the other is the augend.
黑板上没那么多空间写这么长的名字了
But I don't have enough space on the blackboard to such long names.
我就姑且把它们叫做 A1和A2
So I'll call them A1 and A2.
把它们求和
I want to make a sum.
（意义不明）
Do you remember which is the sub for head or the menu end?
是叫做被除数和除数一类的么？
Or was it the dividend and the divisor or something like that?
将A1的导数...加上
Make sum of the derivative of the A1, I'll call it.
这是关于变量VAR的表达式的加数
It's the addend of the expression with respect to the variable,
与A2的导数相加
and the derivative of the A2 of the expression,
这两个参数的和 变量是VAR
those the two arguments, the addition. Respect to the variable.
我们知道还有一条乘法的求导法则
And another rule that we know is product rule,
也就是说 如果表达式是乘式
which is, if the expression is a product.
顺便说下 当你定义过程时 有个好习惯
By the way, it's a good idea when you're defining things,
就是在定义谓词时
when you're defining predicates,
将谓词名以问号结尾
to give them a name that ends in a question mark.
问号本身不代表什么
This question mark doesn't mean anything.
但这是俗成的约定
It's for us as an agreement.
这是人们之间约定的接口 以方便他人阅读你的脚本
It's a conventional interface between humans so you can read my programs more easily.
我希望你在写程序的时候
So I want you to, when you write programs,
当你定义谓词的时候
if you define a predicate procedure,
就是那些返回TRUE或FALSE的过程
that's something that returns true of false,
你应该使它们的名字以问号结尾
it should have a name which ends in question mark.
这对Lisp无异 但对人类友好
The lisp doesn't care. I care.
我需要求和
I want to make a sum.
因为积的导数就是...
Because the product, the derivative of a product is the sum
M1*DERIV(M2)
of the first times the derivative of the second plus
+DERIV(M1)*M2
the second times the derivative of the first.
两者加起来
Make a sum of two things,
求积... 呃 就用表达式中的M1来表示（被乘数）好了
a product of, well, I'm going to say the M1 of the expression,
表达式中M2关于变量VAR的导数
and the derivative of the M2 of the expression with respect to the variable,
以及 M1关于变量VAR的导数乘以
and the product of the derivative of M1,
M1是这里的被乘数
the multiplier of the expression, with respect to the variable.
乘数是表达式中的M2
And the product of that and the multiplicand, M2, of the expression.
求积完毕、求和完毕、乘式分析完毕
Make that product. Make the sum. Close that case.
当然 在这里我可以添加更多的情况
And, of course, I could add as many cases as I like here
微积分书中的完整法则
for a complete set of rules you might find in a calculus book.
我们就是这么来封装这些法则的
So this is what it takes to encapsulate those rules.
如你所见 我们这里用到了大量的“按愿望思维”
And you see, you have to realize there's a lot of wishful thinking here.
我们还没有说这些（表达式）是如何表示的
I haven't told you anything about how I'm going to make these representations.
现在 一旦我将其定为我的一套法则
Now, once I've decided that this is my set of rules,
我想是时候考虑表示法了
I think it's time to play with the representation.
我们来拿捏拿捏
Let's attack that.
首先 我要用到一种“双关”思想
Well, first of all, I'm going to play a pun.
这种“双关”思想非常重要
It's an important pun.
它是一种强有力思想的关键
It's a key to a sort of powerful idea.
如果我想表达诸如和、积、差、商的东西
If I want to represent sums, and products, and differences, and quotients, and things like that,
为什么不用和我程序一样的语言呢？
why not use the same language as I'm writing my program in?
我程序中 代数表达式是形如
I write my program it algebraic expressions that look like
(+ (* A (* X X))
the sum of the product on a and the product of x and x,
和与之类似的
and things like that.
(* B X)以及C
And the product of b and x and c, whatever,
把它们加起来
make that a sum of the product.
现在 我的过程还不能处理多元参数
Right now I don't want to have procedures with unknown numbers of arguments,
(+ (* B X) C)
a product of b and x and c.
这是表结构
This is list structure.
这么做很棒 是因为
And the reason why this is nice,
是因为这些对象都有一种性质
is because any one of these objects has a property.
我知道它们的CAR部分是什么
I know where, know where the car is.
CAR部分就是运算符
The car is the operator.
运算数是相继的CDR部分
And the operands are the successive cdrs
也就是不断取表CDR部分的CAR部分
the successive cars of the cdrs of the list that this is.
这样就使它很方便了
It makes it very convenient.
我需要去解析它 但它已经帮我完成了
Ir have to parse it. It's been done for me.
我利用了Lisp中的内建元素
I'm using the embedding in Lisp to advantage.
举个例子
So, for example,
我们用表结构来表示我所暗示的表示法吧！
Let's start using list structure to write down the representation that I'm implicitly assuming here.
我需要定义一些东西 这都暗含在这种表示法中
Well I have to define various things that are implied in this representation.
比如如何判定是否为常量
Like I have to find out how to do a constant,
又怎么判断是同一个变量
how you do same variable.
我们先完成这些吧 都相当简单
Let's do those first. That's pretty easy enough.
这里 我要介绍一些基本过程
Now I'm going to be introducing lots of primitives here,
因为它们都是与表结构相关的
because these are the primitives that come with list structure.
CONSTANT?谓词定义为
OK, you define a constant.
我所谓的常量
And what I mean by a constant,
表达式关于变量VAR是一个常量
an expression is constant with respect to a variable.
是一些简单的表达式
is that the expression is something simple.
我无法再细化它 但它也不是我们关心的变量
I can't take it into pieces, and yet it isn't that variable.
我无法分解它 但它也不是我们关心的变量
I can't break it up, and yet it isn't that variable.
这也并不是说 一些复杂的表达式就不是常量表达式
That does not mean that there may be other expressions that are more complicated that are constants.
我只是想用这种方式考察基本常量
It's just that I'm going to look at the primitive constants in this way.
因此 这个谓词是几个条件的合取
So what this is, is it says that's it's the and.
AND语句允许用户组合返回TRUE或者FALSE的谓词
I can combine predicate expressions which return true or false with and.
表达式是原子的么？--原子表达式不可以再被细分
Something atomic, The expression is atomic, meaning it cannot be broken into parts.
它没有CAR部分和CDR部分
It doesn't have a car and a cdr.
它不是表
It's not a list.
系统中内建有特殊测试
And it's a special test built into the system.
并且表达式EXP和变量VAR在EQ?的语义下不相等
And it's not identically equal to that variable.
我用不能被分解的符号来表示变量
I'm representing my variables by things that are symbols which cannot be broken into pieces,
比如'X 'Y 和像这样的
things like x, and y, things like this.
当然 像这样的组合式就可以再被细分
Whereas, of course, something like this can be broken up into pieces.
(SAME-VAR? EXP VAR)定义为
And the same variable of an expression with respect to a variable is,
实际上 一条原子表达式……
in fact, an atomic expression.
该表达式与讨论变量相同
I want to have an atomic expression, which is identical.
我不想深入讨论这些过程内部
I don't want to look inside this, this stuff anymore.
把这些当作基本过程
These are primitive maybe.
这无关紧要
But it doesn't matter.
我用的是语言内置的功能
I'm defining... I'm using things that are given to me with a language.
我并不关心这些（具体实现）
I'm not terribly interest in them.
现在 我们要如何处理和式呢？
Now how do we deal with sums?
啊哈 好戏就要上演了
Ah, something very interesting will happen.
和式不是原子的 它以‘+’号打头
A sum is something which is not atomic and begins with the plus symbol.
就是这个意思
That's what it means.
这里 我定义
So here, I will define.
表达式为和式 当它不是原子表达式
An expression is a sum if and it's not atomic
并且它的开头 表达式的CAR部分是个‘+’号
and it's head, it's beginning, its car of the expression is the symbol plus.
我将要引入一个你们从未见过的东西--这个引号
Now you're about to see something you haven't seen before, this quotation.
我这里为什么要用引号呢？
Why do I have that quotation there?
教授：说你的名字
PROFESSOR: Say your name,
观众：Susanna
AUDIENCE: Susanna.
教授：大点声儿
PROFESSOR: Louder.
观众：Susanna
AUDIENCE: Susanna
教授：说“你的名字”
PROFESSOR: Say your name.
观众：“你的名字”
AUDIENCE: Your name.
教授：大点声儿
PROFESSOR: Louder.
观众：“你的名字”
AUDIENCE: Your name.
教授：对了
PROFESSOR: OK.
在这里我想告诉大家 英语词汇是有歧义的
What I'm showing you here is that the words of English are ambiguous.
我可能说 “说你的名字”
I was saying, say your name.
我也可能说 “说‘你的名字’”
I was also possibly saying say, your name.
光从说话上还无法分辨
But that cannot be distinguished in speech.
然而书面上 我们有专门的记号--引号
However, we do have a notation in writing,
用来区别这两种可能的意思
which is quotation for distinguishing these two possible meanings.
具体来说 这里
In particular, over here,
在Lisp中有用于区别这些语义的记号
in Lisp we have a notation for distinguishing these meanings.
如果我只是写下一个加号
If I were to just write a plus here, a plus symbol,
我会问系统 表达式的首元素
I would be asking, is the first element of the expression,
也就是表达式的运算符 是加运算符（一个过程）么？
is the operator position of the expression, the addition operator?
我并不知道
I don't know.
我本应该在那里写一个加运算符的
I would have to have written the addition operator there,
但我无法那样做
which I can't write.
而这种方式则是问 这个符号对象是否为
However, this way I'm asking, is this the symbolic object plus,
代表加运算符的符号
which normally stands for the addition operator?
这才是我想要问和知道的问题
That's what I want. That's the question I want to ask.
在我们深入讨论之前
Now before I go any further,
我想要指出 “引用”是一个复杂的概念
I want to point out the quotation is a very complex concept,
语言中引入这个概念将会造成许多麻烦
and adding it to a language causes a great deal of troubles.
请看下面这张幻灯片
Consider the next slide.
这里这个推论没有问题
Here's a deduction which we should all agree with.
这是说 Alyssa聪明而Alyssa是George的妈妈
We have, Alyssa is smart and Alyssa is George's mother.
通过IS建立了一个等式
This is an equality, is.
我们可以从这两个陈述推论出 George的妈妈很聪明
From those two, we can deduce that George's mother is smart.
这是因为我们总可以在表达式中等价替换
Because we can always substitute equals for equals in expressions.
真是这样吗？
Or can we?
这个例子说 “Chicago”有七个字母
Here's a case where we have "Chicago" has seven letters.
引用则是强调我讨论的是单词“Chicago”
The quotation means that I'm discussing the word Chicago,
而不是单词所代表的意思
not what the word represents.
这里说 Chicago是Illinois州最大的城市
Here I have that Chicago is the biggest city in Illinois.
而（代换的）结果是……
As a consequence of this,
我可能会得到 Illinois州最大的城市有七个字母
I would like to deduce that the biggest city in Illinois has seven letters.
这显然是错的
But that's manifestly false.
喔！手写笔好使了
Wow, it works.
所以 一旦我们有了（引用）这样的东西
OK, so once we have things like that,
我们的语言就会变得复杂
our language gets much more complicated.
因为我们对于语言的一些操作就不再正确
Because it's no longer true that things we tend to like to do with languages,
比如通过等价代换来得到正确答案
like substituting equals for equals and getting right answers,
如果不小心地操作就会出错
are going to work without being very careful.
在一个引用不透明的上下文中 我们无法进行代换
We can't substitute into what's called referentially opaque contexts,
引用就是引用不透明上下文的典型
of which a quotation is the prototypical type of referentially opaque context.
如果你知道那是什么意思……你可以成为一位哲学家
If you know what that means, you can consult a philosopher.
或许我们之中就有一位
Presumably there is one in the room.
言归正传 我们继续
In any case, let's continue now,
现在我们对一个有2000年历史的问题至少有了操作上的理解
now that we at least have an operational understanding of a 2000-year-old issue
关于名称、提及和等等类似的问题
that has to do with name, and mention, and all sorts of things like that.
我得定义如何把两个数加起来 (DEFINE (MAKE-SUM A1 A2))
I have to define what I mean, how to make a sum of two things, an a1 and a2.
我简单实现一下
And I'm going to do this very simply.
'+、A1、A2构成列表
It's a list of the symbol plus, and a1, and a2.
我可以决定如何取出第一个元素
And I can determine the first element.
(DEFINE A1 CADR)
Define a1 to be cadr.
这里又给大家介绍了一个基本过程
I've just introduced another primitive.
这个是取出某物CDR部分的CAR部分
This is the car of the cdr of something.
大家或许会好奇 这些基本过程为什么叫做CAR和CDR
You might want to know why car and cdr are names of these primitives,
而且传承了下来 尽管叫做LEFT和RIGHT会好一点
and why they've survived, even though they're much better ideas like left and right.
我们本可以那样叫的
We could have called them things like that.
呃 其实 这个名字来自于很久以前 当发明Lisp时
Well, first of all, the names come from the fact that in the great past, when Lisp was invented,
我想大概是58年的样子 是在类似于704之类的机子上实现的
I suppose in '58 or something, it was on a 704 or something like that,
这个机器有个地址寄存器和减量寄存器
which had a machine. It was a machine that had an address register and a decrement register.
而这些就是地址寄存器和减量寄存器的值
And these were the contents of the address register and the decrement register.
所以这是历史遗留问题
So it's an historical accident.
但是这些名字为什么又延续下来了呢？
Now why have these names survived?
这是因为Lisp程序员喜欢用电话交流
It's because Lisp programmers like to talk to each other over the phone.
要是你有一长串的CAR和CDR序列 你就可能说“CDADDEDR”
And if you want to have a long sequence of cars and cdrs you might say, cdaddedr,
这是可以理解的
which can be understood.
但是左边的右边的右边的左边就不是那么清楚了
But left of right or right of left is not so clear if you get good at it.
这就是我们为什么有这些黑话
So that's why we have these words.
典型的Lisp系统 默认定义到第四层
All of them up to four deep are defined typically in a Lisp system.
而定义A2为……当然 如果我们考察这些表达式中的一个
A2 to be-- and, of course, you can see that if I looked at one of these expressions
比如(+ 3 5)
like the sum of 3 and 5,
这个实际上是一个包含有'+、数3和数5的表
what that is is a list containing the symbol plus, and a number 3, and a number 5.
表的CAR部分是'+
Then the car is the symbol plus.
CDR部分的CAR部分
The car of the cdr.
也就是先取CDR部分 然后再取CAR部分
Well I take the cdr and then I take the car.
这就是我如何取得3的 也就是第一个参数
And that's how I get to the 3. That's the first argument.
CDR的CDR部分的CAR部分 就是这个……数5
And the car of the cdr of the cdr gets me to this one, the 5.
当然类似地 对于乘式我可以这样定义
And similarly, of course, I can define what's going on with products.
我快速地演示一下
Let's do that very quickly.
(DEFINE (PRODUCT? EXP))
Is the expression a product?
如果它不是原子的 而且
Yes if and if it's true, that's it's not atomic
EXP的CAR部分与用于表示乘法的符号'*在 EQ?的语义下相等
and it's EQ quote, the asterisk symbol, which is the operator for multiplication.
(DEFINE (MAKE-PRODUCT M1 M2))
Make product of an M1 and an M2 to be list,
(LIST '* M1 M2)
quote, the asterisk operation and M1 and M2.
并定义M1为CADR M2为CADDR
And I define M1 to be cadr and M2 to be caddr.
当你说行话的时候 你就上道了
You get to be a good Lisp programmer because you start talking that way.
你可以取表的CDR 也可以把它们组合起来
You can cdr thing down lists and cons them up and so on.
现在 我们有了原理上完整的求导程序了
Now, now that we have essentially a complete program for finding derivatives,
如果需要的话 你也可以添加更多的规则
you can add more rules if you like.
它又要怎么用呢？
What kind of behavior do we get out of it?
我先把这个笔迹清了
I'll have to clear that x.
恩 假设我在这里定义FOO为
Well, supposing I define foo here
定义FOO为A*X^2+B*X+C
to be the sum of the product of ax square and bx plus c.
跟我们这里看到的是一样的
That's the same thing we see here
这里是用更习见的记号书写的代数表达式
as the algebraic expression written in the more conventional notation over there.
那么 表达式FOO关于X的导数 结果在这里
Well, the derivative of foo with respect to x, which we can see over here,
真是乱得一团糟
is this horrible, horrendous mess.
我期望答案是2*A*X+B
I would like it to be 2ax plus b.
虽然与结果等价 但它并不是我们希望的结果
But it's not. It's equivalent to it.
这是什么呢？
What is it?
我们最初有什么？
I have here, what do I have?
我求X*X的导数
I have the derivative of the product of x and x.
答案是X*1+1*X 这当然没错
Over here is, of course, the sum of x times 1 and 1 times x.
这就是乘数的导数乘以被乘数加上乘数乘以被乘数的导数
Now, well, it's the first times the derivative of the second plus the second times the derivative of the first. It's right.
那就是2X、A*2X就是2AX、0X^2省去 再加上0和这里的一大堆0
That's 2x of course. a times 2x is 2ax plus 0X square doesn't count plus B over here plus a bunch of 0's.
答案是对的
Well the answer is right.
当我们还需要用户额外检验一下 真是糟糕透了
But I give people take off points on an exam for that, sadly enough.
我们下一节再考虑这个内容
Let's worry about that in the next segment.
有疑问吗？
Are there any questions?
请说
Yes?
观众：写加号时不加引号
AUDIENCE: If you had left the quote when you put the plus,
是表示引用加那个过程么？
then would that be referring to the procedure plus
如果有需要的话 是否能在两个过程之间进行比较
and could you do a comparison between that procedure and some other procedure if you wanted to?
教授：问得好！
PROFESSOR: Yes. Good question.
如果我这里不用左引号将这个引住
If I had left this quotation off at this point,
如果我这里不用引号
Okay? If I had left that quotation off at that point,
那么这里我就会引用定义好的加法过程
then I would be referring here to the procedure which is the thing that plus is defined to be.
实际上 我可以比较两个过程是否同一
And indeed, I could compare some procedures with each other for identity.
现在很难从语义上解释
Now what that means is not clear right now.
我现在不想考虑这个问题
I don't like to think about it.
因为我不知道比较过程需要什么
Because I don't know exactly what it would need to compare procedures.
这样做没有意义是有很多原因的
There are reasons why that may make no sense at all.
然而 这些符号我们是可以理解的
However, the symbols, we understand.
这也是我为什么我要将它们引住
And so that's why I put that quote in.
我想讨论出现在这些代码中的符号
I want to talk about the symbol that's apparent on the page.
还有什么问题么？
Any other questions?
好吧 休息一下 谢谢大家
OK. Thank you. Let's take a break.
[音乐]
[JESU, JOY OF MAN'S DESIRING]
《计算机程序的构造和解释》
The Structure And Interpretation of Computer Programs
讲师： 哈罗德·艾伯森教授 及 格兰德·杰·萨斯曼教授
By: Prof. Harold Abelson && Gerald Jay Sussman
《计算机程序的构造和解释》
The Structure And Interpretation of Computer Programs
符号化导数系统、引用
Symbolic Differentiation: Quotation
教授：好 我们继续
PROFESSOR: Well, let's see.
我们编写了一个貌似可行的代数表达式求导程序
We've just developed a fairly plausible program for computing the derivatives of algebraic expressions.
这个程序是不完整的 你需要添加一些规则
It's an incomplete program, if you would like to add more rules.
你可能需要加强这个系统 使得它能够处理
And perhaps you might extend it to deal with uses of addition with any number of arguments
多元加法和多元乘法
and multiplication with any of the number of arguments.
这些都相当简单
And that's all rather easy.
但这里面也有一些瑕疵
However, there was a little fly in that ointment.
回到这张幻灯片来
We go back to this slide.
我们发现 得到的表达式相当乱
We see that the expressions that we get are rather bad.
这个表达式非常糟糕
This is a rather bad expression.
我们是怎么得到这样的表达式的？
How do we get such an expression?
为什么是这样呢？
Why do we have that expression?
我们详细地分析一下这个表达式
Let's look at this expression in some detail.
找出这些片段都是出自哪里
Let's find out where all the pieces come from.
如我们所见 这里的和式
As we see here, we have a sum--
也就是上一小节中给你们提到的
just what I showed you at the end of the last time--
(+ (* X 1) (* 1 X))
of X times 1 plus 1 time X.
是这个乘式的导数
That is a derivative of this product.
也就是A乘上这个的积 这里A不是X的函数
The product of a times that, where a does not depend upon x,
因此A关于X是一个常数
and therefore is constant with respect to x,
导数为这个和式 从这里到这里 再到这里
is this sum, which goes from here all the way through here and through here.
因为这个是乘数乘以被乘数的导数
Because it is the first thing times the derivative of the second
加上被乘数乘以乘数的导数
plus the derivative of the first times the second
我们在黑板上的程序告诉我们确实是这样的
as the program we wrote on the blackboard indicated we should do.
当然 这里B乘以X的积
And, of course, the product of bx over here
被化成了 B*1+0*X
manifests itself as B times 1 plus 0 times X
因为B不是X的函数
because we see that B does not depend upon X.
因此B的导数为0
And so the derivative of B is this 0,
而X对自己求导则为1
and the derivative of X with respect itself is the 1.
这里的加法化成了 这两个导数的和
And, of course, the derivative of the sums over here turn into these two sums of the derivatives of the parts.
所以这里 我想告诉你和之前一样的东西
So what we're seeing here is exactly the thing I was trying to tell you about
也就是在讲斐波那契数那时候
with Fibonacci numbers a while ago,
所谓的 “过程的形状”
that the form of the process
就是通过局部的规则向低层次展开
is expanded as low as from the local rules that you see in the procedure,
也就是过程代表了一系列用于演进过程局部规则
that the procedure represents a set of local rules for the expansion of this process.
这里 过程还遗留了一些东西--也就是答案
And here, the process left behind some stuff, which is the answer.
这是通过遍历表达式的树结构构造出来的
And it was constructed by the walk it takes of the tree structure, which is the expression.
答案中的每个部分对应问题中的某个部分
So every part in the answer we see here derives from some part of the problem.
比如说 现在我们考察FOO的导数
Now, we can look at, for example, the derivative of foo,
也就是AX^2+BX+C
which is ax square plus bx plus c,
并另令自变量 比如像这里
with respect to other things, like here, for example,
我们令A为自变量 求FOO的导数
we can see that the derivative of foo with respect to a.
这都非常相似 实际上 它们是同样的代数表达式
And it's very similar. It's, in fact, the identical algebraic expression,
只是它们之中0和1的位置不一样罢了
except for the fact that theses 0's and 1's are in different places.
这是因为在这个树结构的遍历中
Because the only degree of freedom we have in this tree walk
只可能是CONSTANT?和SAME-VAR?会因变量的不同
is what's constant with respect to the variable we're taking the derivative with respect to
而造成不同结果
and what's the same variable.
回到黑板上来再看看
In other words, if we go back to this blackboard and we look,
我们在求和式或乘式的导数时根本没有发挥的余地
we have no choice what to do when we take the derivative of the sum or a product.
真正可以做文章的地方 则是表达式和自变量
The only interesting place here is, is the expression the variable,
以及对于那些短小的表达式 是否为关于自变量的常量
or is the expression a constant with respect to that variable for very, very small expressions?
就是这些地方导致了不同的0和1的产生
In which case we get various 1's and 0's,
回过头来看这张幻灯
which if we go back to this slide,
这里就出现了“0”
we can see that the 0's that appear here, for example,
这里是求FOO(A)的导数时得到的“1”
this 1 over here in derivative of foo with respect to A,
我们得到了X^2
which gets us an X square,
这个1是X*X关于X的导数 关于B求导时1变成了0
because that 1 gets the multiply of X and X into the answer, that 1 is 0.
这里 我们求FOO关于C的导数
Over here, we're not taking the derivative of foo with respect to c.
但是这些表达式的轮廓是一致的
But the shapes of these expressions are the same.
看看这些轮廓 都是相同的
See all those shapes. They're the same.
那么 难道是我们的规则出了问题？
Well is there anything wrong with our rules?
不 这些规则都对
No. They're the right rules.
我们曾经遇到过这种问题
We've been through this one before.
你将会发现 这其中缺乏一些非常好的思想
One of the things you're going to begin to discover is that there aren't too many good ideas.
昨天 我们在考察有理数时
When we were looking at rational numbers yesterday,
想要得到3/4却得到6/8
the problem was that we got 6/8 rather then 3/4.
答案没有化简
The answer was unsimplified.
当然 当下的问题也非常类似
The problem, of course, is very similar.
我想把不相同的表达式通过化简来使相同
There are things I'd like to be identical by simplification that don't become identical.
当然 有理数加法和乘法的规则依然正确
And yet the rules for doing addition a multiplication of rational numbers were correct.
因此这里 我们依葫芦画瓢
So the way we might solve this problem is do the thing we did last time, which always works.
上次能行的办法 这次也没问题
If something worked last time it ought to work again.
也就是改换一下它的表示
It's changed representation.
或许在将其表示出来时我们可以进行
Perhaps in the representation we could put in a simplification step
一步产生简化表示的步骤
that produces a simplified representation.
当然啦 这也不是万用万灵
This may not always work, of course.
我也不想证明它是万能的
I'm not trying to say that it always works.
但这也是控制复杂度的一招妙计
But it's one of the pieces of artillery we have in our war against complexity.
我们小心翼翼地解决这些问题
You see, because we solved our problem very carefully.
我们所做的 就是把问题划分为几个部分
What we've done, is we've divided the world in several parts.
分别是求导规则
There are derivatives rules
和在这种层面上的一般代数规则
and general rules for algebra of some sort at this level of detail.
然后就有一道抽象屏障
and i have an abstraction barrier.
这里是代数表达式的表示--表结构
And i have the representation of the algebraic expressions, list structure.
在这道屏障中 我定义了接口过程
And in this barrier, I have the interface procedures.
比如 CONSTANT? SAME-VAR?
I have constant, and things like same-var.
又比如 SUM? MAKE-SUM
I have things like sum, make-sum.
还有 A1 A2
I have A1, A2.
还有 PRODUCT? 之类的东西
I have products and things like that,
我所需要的、针对各式代数表达式的东西
all the other things I might need for various kinds of algebraic expressions.
构筑这些屏障我可以随意地改换表示法
Making this barrier allows me to arbitrarily change the representation
而不用改变在某种表示法下编写的规则
without changing the rules that are written in terms of that representation.
如果我能通过改变表示法来解决问题
So if I can make the problem go away by changing representation,
那么把问题分解为两个部分则帮了我大忙
the composition of the problem into these two parts has helped me a great deal.
好吧 举一个非常简单的例子
So let's take a very simple case of this.
我们的问题是什么？
What was one of the problems?
回到这张幻灯片来
Let's go back to this transparency again.
看这里 哦 这相当糟糕
And we see here, oh yes, there's horrible things
这里是一个表达式与“0”的和
like here is the sum of an expression and 0.
毋庸置疑这应该是该表达式本身
Well that's no reason to think of it as anything other than the expression itself.
为什么这里还会有加号？
Why should the summation operation have made up this edition?
这其实可以更智能点
It can be smarter than that.
又比如说这里 是某表达式与“1”的积
Or here, for example, is a multiplication of something by 1.
这和之前一个道理
It's another thing like that.
又像这里 与“0”相乘显然是“0”
Or here is a product of something with 0, which is certainly 0.
因此我们也不用去构造这些式子了
So we won't have to make this construction.
我们为什么不这么做呢？
So why don't we just do that?
我们需要去修改表示法 基本上就是那里了
We need to change the way the representation works, almost here.
定义 MAKE-SUM 为
Make-sum to be.
呃 现在就不是那么简单了
Well, now it's not something so simple.
除非是有必要 否则我不会简单地把加号和式子组合成表
I'm not going to make a list containing the symbol plus and things unless I need to.
那么 还有哪些可能呢？
Well, what are the possibilities?
如果……这里有一些可能的情况
If...I have some sort of cases here.
如果都是数值的话 如果A1是数值的话
If I have numbers, if a1 is a number--
这个基本过程我刚刚提到过
and here's another primitive I've just introduced,
也就是用来检测参数是否为数值
it's possible to tell whether something's number--
并且A2也是数值的话 也就是A2不是符号表达式
and if number A2, meaning they're not symbolic expressions,
那么我们就直接把它们加起来
then why not do the addition now?
结果就是A1加上A2的和
The result is just a plus of A1 and A2.
我并不是检查它们代表数值
I'm not asking if these represent numbers.
这里所有的符号都代表数值
Of course all of these symbols represent numbers.
就比如 我想要考察的是这个东西是否为数值3
I'm talking about whether the one I've got is the number 3 right now.
另一种情况
And, for example,
假设A1是数值 并且为0
supposing A1 is a number, and it's equal to 0,
那么答案就是A2
well then the answer is just A2.
不用再构造什么
There is no reason to make anything up.
如果A2是数值 并且为0
And if A2 is a number, and equal A2 0,
那么答案就是A1
then the result is A1.
如果没有比这些更好的情况
And only if I can't figure out something better to do with this situation,
我就需要构造一个表
well, I can construct a list.
构造一个用于表示答案的表
Otherwise I want the representation to be the list
其中有 '+、A1和A2
containing the quoted symbol plus, and A1, and A2.
当然 积的导数也可以类比此法
And, of course, a very similar thing can be done for products.
这里 我就不细讲了
And I think I'll avoid boring you with them.
我就直接在黑板上写出结果
I was going to write it on the blackboard.
这并不是很重要 你们已经了解它的思想了
I don't think it's necessary. You know what to do.
非常简明
It's very simple.
现在 我们来看看用这种方式改造程序后 效果如何
But now, let's just see the kind of results we get out of changing our program in this way.
哦 这是修改表达式构造函数后的求导结果
Well, here's the derivatives after having just changed the constructors for expressions.
对同样地FOO求导：AX^2+BX+C
The same foo, aX square plus bX plus c,
我得到了 2AX+B
and what I get is nothing more than the derivative of that is 2aX plus B.
虽然它并没有化到最简
Well, it's not completely simplified.
我应该合并同类项和求和
I would like to collect common terms and sums.
但这又是另外一回事了
Well, that's more work.
当然啦 完成这个功能的代码就大而复杂了
And, of course, programs to do this sort of thing are huge and complicated.
代数化简 是一项繁复的工作
Algebraic simplification, it's a very complicated mess.
你们可能听过MIT以前开发的一个非常出名的程序 MAXIMA
There's a very famous program you may have heard of called Maxima developed at MIT in the past,
它有5000页的LISP代码
which is 5,000 pages of Lisp code,
大部分是代数化简的操作
mostly the algebraic simplification operations.
这里是FOO的导数
There we see the derivative of foo.
要是我的话 我会在初等微积分课上讲讲“改换主变量”这个东西
In fact, alias is something I wouldn't take off more than 1 point for on an elementary calculus class.
以A为自变量 FOO的导数则是X*X
And the derivative of foo with respect to a, well it's gone down to X times X,
看起来还不差
which isn't so bad.
以B为自变量 FOO的导数则是X本身
And the derivative of foo with respect to b is just X itself.
以C为自变量 FOO的导数则为“1”
And the derivative of foo with respect to c comes out 1.
我对这些结果很满意
So I'm pretty pleased with this.
你所看到的 都是精心设计、仔细规划的例子
What you've seen is, of course, a little bit contrived, carefully organized example
用以展示如何操作代数表达式
to show you how we can manipulate algebraic expressions,
我们如何不用具体的语法 而用抽象的语法抽象地进行
how we do that abstractly in terms of abstract syntax rather than concrete syntax
以及我们如何使用抽象屏障控制构造这些表达式
and how we can use the abstraction to control what goes on in building these expressions.
真正的奥义并不是如此的简单
But the real story isn't just such a simple thing as that.
实际上 真正的奥义在于我在操作这些表达式时
The real story is, in fact, that I'm manipulating these expressions.
代数表达式和代码表达式--
And the expressions are the same expressions--
回过头来看看幻灯片
going back to the slide--
都是同一种Lisp表达式
as the ones that are Lisp expressions.
这样一语双关 一石二鸟
There's a pun here.
我用表示代码相同的方法来作为我的表示法
I've chosen my representation to be the same as the representation in my language of similar things.
为了要这样做 我得付出点代价
By doing so, I've invoked a necessity.
我需要使用类似于“引用”的东西
I created the necessity to have things like quotation
这是因为 我的语言可以编写讨论语言表达式的表达式
because of the fact that my language is capable of writing expressions that talk about expressions of the language.
我需要有某种东西指出 这个是我需要讨论的表达式
I need to have something that says, this is an expression I'm talking about
而不是说 （去求）这个表达式的值
rather than this expression is talking about something,
我想要的是前者
and I want to talk about that.
引用阻止表达式被求值 其语义为“就是表达式本身”
So quotation stops and says, I'm talking about this expression itself.
有了这种能力以后
Now, given that power,
如果我可以操作语言的表达式
if I can manipulate expressions of the language,
我可以在语言层之上构建更加有力的层次
I can begin to build even much more powerful layers upon layers of languages.
因为我可以编写不仅仅是内嵌于Lisp的语言
Because I can write languages that not only are embedded in Lisp
或者是其它的语言
or whatever language you start with,
我可以编写一种完全不同的语言
but languages that are completely different,
而其实质上则是被Lisp或其它语言所解释
that are just, if we say, interpreted in Lisp or something like that.
我们以后还会对此有更深入的理解
We'll get to understand those words more in the future.
我现在只是想让你们意识到
But right now I just want to leave you with the fact that we've hit a line
我们已经感触到了一种惊人的力量
which gives us tremendous power.
现在我们有了方天画戟
And this point we've bought a sledgehammer.
当我们使用它时 也得万分小心
We have to be careful to what flies when we apply it.
谢谢大家
Thank you.
MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
本项目主页
https://github.com/DeathKing/Learning-SICP